Aaagh!
啊！
- Careful, Doctor!  - It's all right. I...
- 小心，博士！  - 没事，我...
I think it's all right now.
我觉得现在没事了
Yes. You see. It's just a mock-up, a model.
是的，你看。这只是一个样机，一个模型
Don't touch that!
That gun may be wired up too.
别碰那个！那把枪可能还没断开
- It's a trap.  - No, I don't think so.
- 这是个陷阱  - 不，我不觉得
It's a testing room for weapons.
这是一间武器测试室
This is a purely robotic Cyberman.
这纯粹只是个机械赛博人
There's no human material in it at all.
里面没有任何人类材料
It's a target for weapons.
它是武器的靶子
Let's get back to the control room
with this poor fellow.
我们回到控制室吧，带上这个可怜的家伙
What's that?
那是什么？
(JAMIE) Some wee creature
I found on the floor.
我在地板上找到的小怪物
It's a fossil.
像是个化石
Victoria, be careful! Let me see that.
Victoria, 小心！让我看看
Yes, it's certainly inactive,
but it's not a fossil.
是的，它的确是不活跃了，但并不是个化石
Wait a minute.
等一下
Yes. Here we are.
是的，我们找到了
Yes.
是的
It's a Cybermat.
这是个赛博鼠
What's a Cybermat?
赛博鼠是什么？
It's one of those...
I'd leave it alone if I were you.
它是一种...反正如果我是你就不会去碰它
I just don't understand this code.
我死活搞不明白这段编码
The sequence doesn't make complete sense.
这个序列完全没有意义
You, a logician, can't understand it?
你，一个逻辑学家，搞不明白它？
- You must.
- But in the time we have...
- 你必须  - 但我们就这么些时间...
We have plenty of time. You will see.
我们有很多时间，你会发现的
- Lay him down there.
- What has happened to him?
- 把他在这里放下吧  - 他怎么了？
There's been a terrible accident.
He's been shot.
发生了一次可怕的意外，他被枪击了
Right. We're all here, it seems.
Would you all sit down for a moment?
好，看起来我们都到了。你们都坐下来歇一会儿吗？
Toberman?
Toberman?﻿
Mr Klieg?
Klieg 先生？
Leave me alone. Can't you see I'm working?
别烦我，你没看见我正在工作吗？
Have you forgotten
the purpose of this expedition?
你已经忘记这次探险的目的了？
This directly concerns my expedition.
You will kindly take your place.
这直接关系到我的探险。请你去就坐
Right. I'll come straight to the point.
好，那我就开门见山了
I have reluctantly decided to abandon
the expedition and return to Earth.
我很不情愿地决定，放弃这次探险，回地球去
- It's impossible!
- I feel just as strongly about it as you.
- 这不可能！  - 我对此也有与你们一样强烈的感觉
This expedition has been
my dream for many years.
这次探险是我多年的梦想
There were some, like Mr Viner,
said more preparation was needed -
曾经有些人，比如 Viner 先生，说过需要做更多准备
more men and equipment.
更多的人和设备
I refused to heed their warnings,
and the result is that two have died.
我没有重视这些警告，结果是有两个人死掉了
I'm sorry, but we must leave
at the first available conjunction.
我很抱歉，但我们必须在第一次有可用连接时就离开
We'll take back all we can
for further study of course.
当然，我们尽可能带走一些东西，以供后续研究
But that is my decision
and that is what we must do.
但这是我的决定，也是我们必须要做的
- I insist that...!
- My decision is final!
- 我坚持认为...  - 我这是最后决定！
We leave when the north hemisphere
is properly tangential,
当北半球转到合适的切向时，我们就走
which will be at 18.42.
也就是大约在18:42
Ah, Captain Hopper. Just the man.
啊，Hopper 队长，正要找你呢
- Can you be ready to blast off at 18.42?
- No.
- 你能准备好在18:42升空吗？  - 不能
I beg your pardon. Did I hear you right?
对不起，我没听错吧？
You are paid to take orders.
你拿了钱，就得遵从命令
Not impossible ones.
但做不到的命令就遵从不了
It's the fuel pumps.
Some character has balled-up the lot.
是燃油泵，某个人把它们破坏了
- What?  - Or someTHING.
- 什么？  - 或者是某个东西
Whatever it is, it's practically wrecked
our chances of leaving this planet.
不管是什么，基本上把我们离开这个星球的机会给破坏了
There's no doubt about it.
The major workings lie below.
毫无疑问，主要的工事都在下面
There are metal caverns
down there, all interconnected.
下面有两个金属窟窿，相互连接
If only we can get down to them.
要是我们能下到那里就好了
That's it! I've got it!
对了，我明白了！
Finally, a Boolean function
of symbolic logic.
最终，还是一个符号逻辑的布尔函数
- Logical, yes, but...
- Everything yields to logic.
- 有逻辑的，是，但是...  - 一切都暗合逻辑
- Our basic assumption, Doctor  - Really.
- 这是我们基本的假设，博士  - 真是
Six, cap, B4...
6与B4取交集
if and only if C
当且仅当C
is cap function of 2A.
得到交集函数2A
I think perhaps your logic
is wearing a little thin.
我看你的逻辑有点站不住脚啊
I must have made a mistake.
I'll do it again more carefully.
我肯定犯了一个错误。我再仔细来一遍
Six, cap, B4...
6与B4取交集
if and only if C...
当且仅当C
is cap faction of... Ah, that's it!
得到交集函数...啊，就是它了
2F, not 2A.
是 2F 不是 2A
(WHIRRING)
I've done it! I've done it!
我搞定了！我搞定了！
- Congratulations!  - But, Doctor, you...
- 恭喜恭喜  - 但是，博士，你...
Excellent. Now to work.
很好，现在去干活吧
It'll be extremely cold down there.
We shall all need to put on warm clothing.
下面极其冷，我们都得穿上保暖的衣服
Mr Viner, would you please get the anoraks?
Viner 先生，你能去把防寒服取来吗？
- Just a moment. Are we all going down?
- There's safety in numbers.
- 等一下，我们都要下去吗  - 人多安全些
- The women as well?
- They will of course stay up here.
- 女人也下去？  - 她们当然留在这上面
In case of trouble, contact the rocket.
万一遇到麻烦，联系火箭
- I'm coming down with you.
- But my dear young lady...
- 我跟你们下去  - 但是我亲爱的小姐...
- You heard me, Professor.  - Victoria.
- 你听到我的话了，教授  - Victoria
You will be much safer up here.
你在上面这里会安全得多
- But, Doctor...  - And much more use to us.
- 但是, 博士...  - 而且对我们更有用
- I don't see...
- By keeping an eye on things.
- 我看不出...  - 有些事情可以盯着点
Please.
拜托了
- All right.  - Thank you.
- 没事了  - 谢谢你
(PARRY) If we're all ready,
I shall lead the descent.
如果我们都准备好了, 我带头下去了
Be ready to go back the instant I give the word.
做好准备, 万一有问题听我消息就马上回来
- You know what to do?  - The hatch?
- 你知道该怎么弄吗？  - 舱门？
Mr Toberman?
Toberman 先生呢？
He stays with me.
他跟我一起留下来
Then I stay here too.
那我也留在这里
Of course. I am being selfish.
当然．我这样太自私了
His strength will be useful to you
down there. He must go down.
他的力气在下面对你们有用, 他必须下去
Go down, Toberman.
下去吧, Toberman
Remember what I said. Be very careful.
记住我说的, 千万小心
(KAFTAN) It seems we are left alone to wait.
看来就剩我们在这里等了
Captain Hopper brought food
from the rocket. You would like some?
Hopper 队长从火箭那边带来了食物, 你要来点吗？
Rather! I'm ravenous.
要！我饿死了
Hurry up, we've no time to linger!
快点，我们没时间磨蹭了！
It's extremely cold down here,
even with these anoraks.
下面极其寒冷, 这些保暖服也太不管用
(JAMIE) You obviously knew what to expect.
你显然早知道会有什么
Well, which way do we go?
喏, 我们走那条路？
I don't know. Let's try this one.
我不知道, 我们试试这边
Yes.
好
Hey, what on Earth?!
嘿, 这是什么鬼？
(PARRY) Behold, gentlemen,
the tombs of the Cybermen.
看啊, 先生们, 赛博人的坟墓
(JAMIE) Tombs? I don't see any tombs.
坟墓？我没看到什么坟墓
There, Jamie.
那儿, Jamie
Frozen forever.
永久冻住的
All their evil locked away with them.
他们的邪恶也一并被锁住了
And so it must remain.
而且必须一直保持这样
Like a gigantic honeycomb.
就像一个巨大的蜂巢
Like bees waiting for the signal
to arise from their winter sleep.
就像蜜蜂一样, 等着一个信号, 从他们的冬眠中苏醒
A signal they are never going to get.
他们永远也不会得到这个信号
We'd better get busy.
Everything must be recorded.
我们动作得快点, 所有东西都要录下来
It's too cold to remain here for long
这里太冷了，可没法待太久
Unless we find some way to warm things up.
除非我们能找到什么方法让这里暖和起来
You have hardly touched your coffee.
你的咖啡没怎么动啊
It must be cold by now.
这会儿肯定已经冷了
You would like some more?
你还要再来一点吗？
No, thank you. I'm much warmer now.
不用了, 谢谢你, 我现在暖和多了
That's good.
那就好
I...
我...
feel so sleepy.
觉得好困
(WHIRRING)
(CLANG)
- What was that?
- It sounded like the hatch.
- 那是什么声音？  - 听起来好像是舱门
It's closed!
它被关上了！
What's the use?
We're trapped down here now.
关上做什么？我们现在被困在下面了
We'll never survive in this cold.
在这么冷的地方我们没法存活
Better get back.
最好是回去
Well?
怎样？
It's closed. What have they done that for?
What are they playing at up there?
被关上了．他们为什么这么做？他们在上面玩什么啊？
Maybe it wasn't them. Where's Jamie?
也许不是他们．Jamie 那里去了？
He went up the ladder to try it.
他上梯子去试试
Professor. Professor, listen to me,
for heaven's sake!
教授, 教授, 听我说, 老天
The hatch is down again.
We're trapped down here.
舱门又降下来了, 我们被困在下面了
But some of my party
are up there. Are you sure?
但我有一部分人在上面．你确定吗？
Of course I'm sure. You know how heavy it is.
我当然确定, 你知道它有多重
It's down now. We must do something!
现在关上了。我们必须做点什么！
I'll give us a couple of hours in here at most.
我觉得我们在这里最多能待几个小时
Mr Klieg doesn't seem to be very worried.
Klieg 似乎并不怎么担心
No, I'm not, Doctor.
不, 我不担心, 博士
It won't open and I can't make them hear.
它不会打开, 我也没法让他们听见
There is an easy way out of our situation.
有一个简单的方法跳出当前的困境
- You've found something?
- Of cource, you're forgetting the logic.
- 你发现了什么吗？  - 当然， 你们忘记了逻辑
If it closes, it can be opened
- from here.
如果它关上了, 就可以被打开 - 从这里打开
Conveniently labelled
in symbolic logic, I noticed.
已经很贴心地用符号逻辑标上了 - 我注意到了
Right. Are we ready?
I shall now operate the sequence.
对．我们准备好了, 我要开始操作了
If it is the opening device.
只要这是开启装置
It's obvious an opening device
of some kind, Doctor.
这很显然是某种开启装置, 博士
I don't know how you can be
so blasted calm about it!
我不知道你们怎么能这么冷静！
I'll see if it works then.
我来看看它是否能工作
Go ahead!
开始吧！
Nothing happening out here!
这里什么也没有发生！
It doesn't work.
它没起作用
Water!
水！
- It's getting warmer.
- The ice is melting.
- 变热了  - 冰在融化
Hey, look behind you!
嘿, 看看你后面
Look!
看
Look at the honeycomb.
快看蜂巢
There's something inside.
里面有什么东西
They're... They're Cybermen.
那些是...那些是赛博人
Jamie, come back!
Jamie, 回来！
It is them.
是他们
Gentlemen, they are perfect.
先生们, 他们是完好的
This is unique in archaeology.
这在考古学上是独一无二的
No!
不！
No! They're moving!
不！他们在动了！
We must shut it down.
我们必须关掉它
(LOUD WHIRRING)
(WHIRRING WINDS DOWN)
What are you doing? Keep away from that!
你在干什么？离那个远点！
No.
不
- What are you doing?
- Keep away! I shall not hesitate to kill!
- 你在干什么！  - 一边去！我开枪是不会犹豫的!
For the last time, I'm asking you
to keep away from those controls.
最后一次， 我叫你离开那些开关
No!
不！
Viner!
Viner!​
You've killed him!
你杀了他！
- He's mad.  - Jamie!
- 他疯了  - Jamie!
Haydon dead, now Viner.
Haydon 已经死了, 现在又是 Viner
What kind of man are you?
你是个什么人啊？
Back! Keep back!
后退！后退！
Let's see what happens.
我们看看会发生什么
As the Professor says, this is
a unique archaeological event.
正如教授所说, 这是考古学上的大新闻
It would be such a pity to miss it.
要是错过的话就太遗憾了
(LOUD WHIRRING)
Doctor, I have a feeling
that man's planned it all.
博士, 我有一种感觉, 那个人早就计划好了
He knew that wouldn't open the hatch.
他知道那个东西不能打开舱门
- So did I, Jamie.  - You knew, Doctor?
- 我也觉得, Jamie  - 你早知道，博士？
I wanted to know what he was up to.
我想要知道他在谋划什么
- And now you know, Doctor.
- We know nothing.
- 现在你知道了, 博士  - 我们什么也不知道
This is the action of a lunatic.
这是一个疯子才会干的事情
Lunatic? Not at all, Professor.
A necessary detail, that's all.
疯子？完全不是, 教授．这是必要的步骤, 仅此而已
But why?
但为什么？
Logic, my dear Professor, logic and power.
逻辑, 我亲爱的教授, 逻辑和权力
On Earth, the Brotherhood of Logicians
在地球上, 逻辑兄弟会
is the greatest man intelligence
ever assembled.
集结了最聪明的人
But that's not enough. We need power -
但这还不够, 我们需要权力
power to put our ability into action.
可以将我们的能力变成行动的权力
The Cybermen have this power.
I have come to find it and use it.
赛博人有这个力量, 我就是来找到它利用它的
So that was your motive
in financing my expedition!
这就是你资助我们探险队的动机！
Precisely. Your complete lack of administration
made it ideal for our purpose.
正是．你完全缺乏管理, 这对于我们的目的相当理想
You think the Cybermen will help you?
你觉得赛博人会帮助你？
Of course. I shall be their resurrector.
当然, 我是复兴他们的人
Look!
快看！
- Keep still!   - Behind you!
- 待着别动！  - 在你后面！
That thing! It's come alive!
那个东西！它活过来了！
You are so simple. You don't really expect
to take me in with a trick like that?
你太单纯了, 真的别想用这样的技巧诓骗我
It's true! Look!
是真的, 快看！
- Will nothing keep you still?
- Will you please look?!
- 没什么能让你安静吗？  - 求你能看一下吗？
(BEEPING)
Any more trouble and I'll take drastic steps.
再要捣乱, 我就要采取极端措施了
We won't allow a little girl
to interfere with our plan!
我们不会容许一个小女儿来破坏我们的计划！
Aaagh!
啊！
(BEEPING WINDS DOWN...)
(..AND STOPS)
What is it?
那是什么？
I think it's their leader,
their Controller, Jamie.
我猜是他们的头儿, 他们的管理员, Jamie
(CONTROLLER) You belong to us.
你属于我们
You shall be like us.
你会跟我们一样